

Profile

Software developer with 5 years 6 months experience in java spring boot based web applications along with strong experience in amazon web services. Experience in databricks, snowflake and spark for huge data handling applications. Worked with dockerizing application and deploying them in AWS kubernetes. Hands on experience in developing applications for supporting media processing and delivery. Developed applications using AWS Lambda and Apache Kafka for solving issues and bottleneck in internal applications.

Employment History

Development Engineer 3, Comcast Technology Solutions

NOVEMBER 2022 - PRESENT

- Planning and orchestrating migration of applications to make them compliant with the latest security standards.
- Handling customer issues and workflow setups to make the process seamless during high profile events.
- Sprint planning, coordinating across teams, prioritizing with product management and designing systems for future implementations.
- Training and grooming junior associates and interns.
- Working on new ideas to make the system handle huge loads with lesser wait time.

Development Engineer 2, Comcast Technology Solutions, Chennai

APRIL 2021 - NOVEMBER 2022

- Developed backend services for the platform console which is used for multiple video platform related functions.
- Helped in analysing old services and converting them as dockers and updating related dependencies thereby increasing the availability, security and performance.
- Developed components for the services which decreases the security vulnerabilities of backend services.
- Involved in weekly deliverables involving the enhancements of applications within workflow services.
- Developed a Datadog dashboard to monitor all applications and trigger an alarm if any parameter crosses the desired value.
- Worked with Linux based machine for application maintenance and improvements.
- Incident response and resolution, while working with the customers to find the root cause and prevent future occurrences.
- Setting alerting system to take proactive measure to avoid any outage or performance shortfall in the system.
- Training interns with necessary technical skills to be a part of the team.

Program analyst, Cognizant Technology Solutions, Chennai

DECEMBER 2017 - APRIL 2021

- Developed backend apps for student performance dashboard which involves handling large data with minimal time using graphql and java 8 features.
- Helped reducing Amazon RDS cost by analysing tables and information from solar winds to lower the overall size and complications.

Details

8870382673 kailuneel1995@gmail.com

Skills

MySQL

Java

Amazon AWS

Databricks

Snowflake

SQL

NewRelics

GraphQL

Microservices

Ansible

Spring boot

Python

Linux

Scala

Shell Script

Kubernetes

Docker

Apache Kafka

Hobbies

Digital art, Technology news, Casual gaming

- Developed a data transfer system which efficiently exports and transforms data from MsSql db to RDS MySql db using databricks and snowflake db which eliminated legacy complications and made the process much faster and cost efficient.
- Developed a report generation system with databricks which created reports for universities from MySql DB using Databricks to store the documents as encrypted downloadable format in amazon S3.
- Developed a NewRelic dashboard to monitor all applications and trigger an alarm if any parameter crosses the desired value.
- Worked with Linux based machine for application maintenance and improvements.

Project Details

Pearson, Denver

Pearson's very strong competitive & commercial performance in Higher Education over the last decade can be attributed to our success in delivering effective digital courseware at scale through its products (My Labs, Mastering & Revel). These Products enabled digress of personalization, but are largely one-size-fits-all and provide limited adaptive learning.

Comcast, Seattle

Comcast Corporation is an American multinational telecommunications conglomerate headquartered in Philadelphia, Pennsylvania. It is the second-largest broadcasting and cable television company in the world by revenue, the largest pay-TV company, the largest cable TV company and largest home Internet service provider in the United States, and the nation's third-largest home telephone service provider.

Roles and responsibilies

AWS Cloud Infrastructure architecting and administration

DECEMBER 2017 - APRIL 2021

- Launching Linux instances from AMIs in highly available and fault tolerant cluster, hardening them, installing required software and configuring them.
- Launching RDS instances in Multi-AZ, securing them with security groups by controlling ingress and egress traffic.
- Creating EC2 instances in AWS to let application servers connect to external
- Creating an ELB, configuring it to achieve high availability and SSL termination.
- Using ROUTE 53/ AKAMAI as DNS service and creating necessary records.

Application developing responsibilities

DECEMBER 2017 - APRIL 2021

- Working on all stages of SDLC for developing a Web Application for PLA in both Front end and Back End using Spring Boot, Restful Web Services, GraphOL
- Creating the Modules as per the client's requirement given in the API Contract Document shared by Domain Engineering Team.
- Performed Requirements Analysis on Process automation projects that involves working with multiple functions and teams across the Balance Sheet Management, Rate Risk, FTP, Stress Test & Performance Test
- Automation of Deployments & Infrastructure creation using Ansible framework

- Writing ETL for getting data from upstream applications using DataBricks, Snowflake, Spring Boot, SQS, Java JDKs, EMR & Shell Scripts
- Production Support for team owned Applications.

Development engineer, Chennai

APRIL 2021 - PRESENT

- Responsible for design and development of features and modules for workflow related services within Comcast.
- Conversion of spring micro services to dockerized applications to run in kubernetes cloud.
- Designing deployment pipelines for micro services within workflow for automated production deployment.
- Worked on hardening applications to make them more secure and updated.
- Completed training on docker and kubernetes and helped the team in implementing the concepts in applications to improve their availability.
- Fixed major issues in existing applications and deployed in prod environment to resolve customer issues.
- Making systems more optimized for heavy loads designing the optimum capacity for the services.
- Handling and fixing customer issues in high availability applications and solving them in a short span of time.

Awards

Pearson Idol

DECEMBER 2018 - DECEMBER 2018

Awarded for good contribution towards the project.

Top Coder for Sep - 20

DECEMBER 2020 - DECEMBER 2020

Independently integrated the data bricks on ETL migration with quality of 0 defects even in QA environment. In Data bricks integration created a customized configuration for on-demand clusters, which helps reducing the instance cost around 30%.

SPOTLIGHT- CHAMP Award

JUNE 2022 - JUNE 2022

Awarded for contribution towards the project and helping team members scale up.

Employee of the quarter

OCTOBER 2022

For the achievement that have been earned during the Q3 - 2022.

Personal Project

Deployer tool, Chennai

OCTOBER 2021 - OCTOBER 2021

Developed a dockerised deployer tool which enhances the existing deployer functionality by increasing availability and user friendly.

Features:

- Modify servicenow CCB status during deployments.
- Notify the specified slack channels about the deployment.
- Ensure the service is up and running.
- Run the DVTs and make sure they pass.

DropFolder, Chennai

OCTOBER 2022 - OCTOBER 2022

A triggered based system to ingest bulk media into Comcast media servers which scales as per requirement .

Project is under customer requirement analysis and is being considered as a feature proposal.

Data Polling, Chennai

MARCH 2023 - MARCH 2023

An alternative approach for polling systems which uses debezium connector to look for changes in binlogs of MySql databases and post it to a kafka topic enabling on demand updates.

Education

Bachelor of engineering, Mepco Schlenk Engineering College, Sivakasi

JUNE 2013 - JUNE 2017

• Score: 88%

Adarsh Vidya Kendra, Nagercoil

JUNE 2000 - APRIL 2012

Xth Score: 80% XII Score: 83%

References

Parthiban Karunanithi from Comcast Technology Solutions

8088672530